<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="ch0001s0001">
   <sect1info>
      <risinfo>
         <risprev>sect1.9781610028370.ch0001s0009</risprev>
         <riscurrent>sect1.9781610028370.ch0001s0001</riscurrent>
         <risnext>sect1.9781610028370.ch0001s0002</risnext>
         <booktitle>Coding for Pediatrics 2026</booktitle>
         <isbn>9781610028370</isbn>
         <chapternumber>1</chapternumber>
         <chapterid>ch0001</chapterid>
         <chaptertitle>Front Matter</chaptertitle>
         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <personname>
                  <firstname>Linda D.</firstname>
                  <surname>Parsi</surname>
               </personname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <publisher>
            <publishername>American Academy of Pediatrics</publishername>
         </publisher>
         <pubdate>2025</pubdate>
      </risinfo>
      <primaryauthor>
         <personname>
            <firstname>Linda D.</firstname>
            <surname>Parsi</surname>
         </personname>
      </primaryauthor>
   </sect1info>
   <title>Coding for Pediatrics 2026</title>
   <sect2 id="ch0001s0001s0001">
      <title>A Manual for Pediatric Documentation and Payment 31ST EDITION</title>
      <para>The 31st edition of this American Academy of Pediatrics (AAP) cornerstone coding publication includes 2026 updates to the <emphasis role="italics">Current Procedural Terminology (CPT®)</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italics">International Classification of Diseases, 10th Revision, Clinical Modification (ICD-10-CM)</emphasis> code sets—complete with expert guidance for their application. The book's many clinical vignettes, examples, and tips help ensure accuracy and timely payment.</para>
      <sect3 id="ch0001s0001s30001">
         <title/>
         <sect4 id="ch0001s0001s0001s01s01">
            <title>Key updates in this edition include</title>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>CPT 2026 code updates</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Coding for immunization counseling when one or more immunizations are not administered</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Appropriate use of new codes for immunization products and administration</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Reporting less than 20 minutes spent in monthly remote physiologic monitoring treatment management</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>New codes for orthopedic and neurological services</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Updated compliance program guidance with examples for small and large practices</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect4>
         <sect4 id="ch0001s0001s0001s01s02">
            <title>Additional Pediatric Coding Resources From the American Academy of Pediatrics</title>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="bold">*AAP Pediatric Coding Newsletter™</emphasis>* Streamline coding with a subscription to the <emphasis role="italics">AAP Pediatric Coding Newsletter</emphasis>. Each issue is packed with time-saving how-to strategies to help your practice reduce errors, avoid over/under-coding, and get payment approved more quickly. It also provides critical code updates, covers correct use of modifiers, and explains how to code for AAP policy statements, clinical reports, and technical reports. Visit <emphasis role="bold">http://publications.aap.org/codingnews</emphasis> to download a sample issue or subscribe today.</para>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="bold">*Pediatric ICD-10-CM 2026: A Manual for Provider-Based Coding, 11th Edition</emphasis>* The completely updated 11th edition includes all new 2026 pediatric <emphasis role="italics">ICD-10-CM</emphasis> codes, including updated or new for birth and obstetric trauma, intracranial injury, chronic kidney disease, paralytic ileus and intestinal obstruction, hepatic failure, chronic hepatitis, and much more.</para>
         </sect4>
      </sect3>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="ch0001s0001s0002">
      <title>To order these and other pediatric coding resources, visit shopAAP</title>
      <para>aap.org/shopaap</para>
      <para>American Academy of Pediatrics</para>
      <para>DEDICATED TO THE HEALTH OF ALL CHILDREN®</para>
      <para>ISBN 978-1-61002-836-3</para>
      <para>90000&gt;</para>
      <para>9 781610 028363</para>
   </sect2>
</sect1>