<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="ch0015s0004">
   <sect1info>
      <risinfo>
         <risprev>sect1.9781610028370.ch0015s0003</risprev>
         <riscurrent>sect1.9781610028370.ch0015s0004</riscurrent>
         <risnext>sect1.9781610028370.ch0015s0005</risnext>
         <booktitle>Coding for Pediatrics 2026</booktitle>
         <isbn>9781610028370</isbn>
         <chapternumber>15</chapternumber>
         <chapterid>ch0015</chapterid>
         <chaptertitle>12. Nonphysician Qualified Health Care Professional Services</chaptertitle>
         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <personname>
                  <firstname>Linda D.</firstname>
                  <surname>Parsi</surname>
               </personname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <publisher>
            <publishername>American Academy of Pediatrics</publishername>
         </publisher>
         <pubdate>2025</pubdate>
      </risinfo>
      <primaryauthor>
         <personname>
            <firstname>Linda D.</firstname>
            <surname>Parsi</surname>
         </personname>
      </primaryauthor>
   </sect1info>
   <title>0362T</title>
   <para>Behavior identification supporting assessment, each 15 minutes of technicians' time face-to-face with a patient, requiring the following components:</para>
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>administration by the physician or other QHP who is on site;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>with the assistance of two or more technicians;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>for a patient who exhibits destructive behavior;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>completion in an environment that is customized to the patient's behavior.</para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>Behavior identification assessment (<emphasis role="bold">97151</emphasis>) is conducted by a physician or other QHP and may include</para>
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>Analysis of pertinent past data, including medical diagnosis</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>A detailed behavioral history</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Patient observation</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Administration of standardized and/or non-standardized instruments and procedures</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Functional behavior assessment</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Functional analysis</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Guardian/caregiver interview to identify and describe deficient adaptive behaviors, maladaptive behaviors, and other impaired functioning secondary to deficient adaptive or maladaptive behaviors</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Documentation should include both of the assessment and a person-centered treatment plan.</para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>If the physician or other QHP personally performs the technician activities, their time engaged in these activities should be included as part of the required technician time to meet the components of the code.</para>
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>Codes <emphasis role="bold">97151, 97152, and 0362T</emphasis> may be repeated on the same or different days until the behavior identification assessment (<emphasis role="bold">97151</emphasis>) and, if necessary, supporting assessment(s) (<emphasis role="bold">97152, 0362T</emphasis>) are complete.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Code <emphasis role="bold">97152</emphasis> is reported for assessment by a technician. The reporting physician or QHP is not required to be on-site during the assessment. Refer to <emphasis role="bold">0362T</emphasis> when multiple technicians and a customized assessment environment are required for a patient who demonstrates destructive behavior(s).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Code <emphasis role="bold">0362T</emphasis> represents testing of a patient who demonstrates destructive behavior (ie, maladaptive behaviors associated with a high risk of medical consequences or property damage) and requires multiple technicians and an environment customized to the patient and behavior. <emphasis role="italics">The reporting physician or QHP is required to be on-site</emphasis> (ie, immediately available and interruptible to provide assistance and direction throughout the performance of the procedure). The reporting physician or QHP is not required to be in the room during testing.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Count the time of only 1 technician when 2 or more technicians are present. Code <emphasis role="bold">0362T</emphasis> is reported according to a single technician's face-to-face time with the patient and not the combined time of multiple technicians (eg, 1 hour with 3 technicians equals 1 hour of service) despite the expectation that more than one technician will be needed.</para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
      <emphasis role="italics">Examples</emphasis> ▶ <emphasis role="bold">A 3-year-old child with characteristics of ASD presents for assessment.</emphasis> The physician/QHP spends 1 hour face-to-face with the patient and/or parent(s)/caregiver(s) administering assessments and discussing findings and recommendations and 38 minutes of non–face-to-face time analyzing past data, scoring/interpreting the assessment, and preparing the report/treatment plan. The total time of service is 98 minutes. Code <emphasis role="bold">97151</emphasis> is reported with 7 units (1 for each full 15 minutes of service and 1 for the last 8 minutes).</para>
   <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Teaching Point:</emphasis> If less than 8 minutes past the last full 15 minutes of service were provided, only the number of 15-minute periods of service would be reported (eg, 1 hour 37 minutes equals 6 units).</para>
   <para>▶<emphasis role="bold">An additional assessment of the 3-year-old from the previous example is required to assess behavior that interferes with acquisition of adaptive skills.</emphasis> A technician, under the physician's or QHP's direction, observes and records occurrences of the patient's deficient adaptive and maladaptive behaviors and the surrounding environmental events several times in a variety of situations. The physician/QHP reviews and analyzes data from the technician's observations. The face-to-face time of the technician is 1 hour.</para>
   <para>Code <emphasis role="bold">97152</emphasis> is reported with 4 units of service.</para>
   <para>▶<emphasis role="bold">An 11-year-old child with ASD requires evaluation to assess increased self-injury and aggression toward others.</emphasis> A team of technicians conducts the assessment session in a room that is devoid of any objects that might cause injury. A physician/QHP is on-site and immediately available throughout the session. The technicians implement functional analysis (ie, they systematically present and withdraw events to the patient multiple times while observing and measuring occurrence of a target behavior) as directed by the physician/QHP and record data. Graphed data are reviewed and analyzed by the physician/QHP to identify the environmental events in whose presence the level of behavior was highest and lowest. The technicians spend a total of 90 minutes face-to-face with the patient during the assessment.</para>
   <para>Code <emphasis role="bold">0362T</emphasis> is reported with 6 units of service.</para>
   <sect2 id="ch0015s0004s20001">
      <title/>
      <sect3 id="ch0015s0004s30008">
         <title/>
         <sect4 id="ch0015s0004s0001s01s01">
            <title>Adaptive Behavior Treatment</title>
            <para>Adaptive behavior treatment services address specific treatment targets and goals based on results of previous assessments and include ongoing assessment and adjustment of treatment protocols, targets, and goals. Codes describe services to an individual patient, groups of patients, families, and an individual patient who exhibits destructive behavior.</para>
            <para>Codes for adaptive behavior treatment specify services provided by protocol (<emphasis role="bold">97153, 97154</emphasis>) or with protocol modification (<emphasis role="bold">97155, 97158, 0373T</emphasis>). Behavior treatment with protocol modification requires adjustments be <emphasis role="italics">made in real time</emphasis> rather than for a subsequent service.</para>
         </sect4>
         <sect4 id="ch0015s0004s0001s01s02">
            <title>Adaptive Behavior Treatment by Protocol (97153–97154)</title>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="bold">#97153</emphasis> Adaptive behavior treatment by protocol, administered by technician under the direction of a physician or other QHP, face-to-face with one patient, each 15 minutes <emphasis role="bold">#97154</emphasis> Group adaptive behavior treatment by protocol, administered by technician under the direction of a physician or other QHP, face-to-face with two or more patients, each 15 minutes</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Adaptive behavior treatment by protocol to a single patient (<emphasis role="bold">97153</emphasis>) and group adaptive behavior treatment by protocol (<emphasis role="bold">97154</emphasis>) administered by a technician under the direction of a physician/QHP, with a treatment protocol <emphasis role="italics">designed in advance</emphasis> by the physician or other QHP, who may or may not provide direction during the treatment.</para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>The service described by <emphasis role="bold">97153</emphasis> is face-to-face with only 1 patient.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>Code <emphasis role="bold">97154</emphasis> is reported for services delivered face-to-face with 2 or more patients but not more than 8 patients.</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Codes <emphasis role="bold">97153</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">97154</emphasis> do not include protocol modification.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>If the physician/QHP personally performs the technician activities, their time spent engaged in these activities should be reported as technician time. The physician is not required to be on-site during the provision of these services.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="italics">Examples</emphasis> ▶ <emphasis role="bold">A 4-year-old child with ASD presents with differences in language and social skills and emotional outbursts in response to small changes in routines or when preferred items are unavailable.</emphasis> A QHP directs a technician in the implementation of treatment protocols and data collection procedures. The technician conducts a treatment session in the family home with multiple planned opportunities for the patient to practice target skills. The QHP reviews the technician's recorded and graphed data to assess the child's progress and determine if any treatment protocol needs adjustment. The technician spends 1 hour at the patient's home with face-to-face time of the treatment session lasting 50 minutes. Code <emphasis role="bold">97153</emphasis> is reported with 3 units of service.</para>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="bold">Teaching Point:</emphasis> Only the technician's face-to-face time with the patient is used to determine the units of service. This service may also be conducted in a community setting (eg, playground, store).</para>
            <para>▶<emphasis role="bold">Peer social skills training in a small group is recommended for a 7-year-old child with differences in social skills resulting from ASD.</emphasis> A technician conducts the group session with treatment protocols and data collection procedures as previously designed by a QHP. The QHP reviews the technician's recorded and graphed data to assess the child's progress and determine if treatment protocols need adjustment. The total face-to-face time of the session is 60 minutes.</para>
            <para>Code <emphasis role="bold">97154</emphasis> is reported with 4 units.</para>
         </sect4>
         <sect4 id="ch0015s0004s0001s01s03">
            <title>Adaptive Behavior Treatment With Protocol Modification (97155, 97158, 0373T)</title>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="bold">#97155</emphasis> Adaptive behavior treatment with protocol modification administered by physician or other QHP, which may include simultaneous direction of technician, face-to-face with one patient, each 15 minutes <emphasis role="bold">#97158</emphasis> Group adaptive behavior treatment with protocol modification, administered by physician or other QHP, face-to-face with multiple patients, each 15 minutes</para>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="bold">0373T</emphasis> Adaptive behavior treatment with protocol modification, each 15 minutes of technicians' time face-to-face with a patient, requiring the following components:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>administration by the physician or other QHP who is on site;</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>with the assistance of two or more technicians;</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>for a patient who exhibits destructive behavior;</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>completion in an environment that is customized to the patient's behavior.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Adaptive behavior treatment with protocol modification (<emphasis role="bold">97155</emphasis>) is administered by a physician/QHP <emphasis role="italics">face-to-face with a single patient</emphasis>.</para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>The physician/QHP resolves one or more problems with the protocol and may simultaneously direct a technician in administering the modified protocol <emphasis role="italics">while the patient is present</emphasis>.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>Physician/QHP direction to the technician without the patient present is not reported separately.</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Group adaptive behavior treatment with protocol modification (<emphasis role="bold">97158</emphasis>) is reported when a physician/QHP provides <emphasis role="italics">face-to-face</emphasis> protocol modification services with up to 8 patients in a group. The physician/QHP monitors the needs of individual patients and adjusts treatment techniques during the group sessions, as needed.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Adaptive behavior treatment with protocol modification (<emphasis role="bold">0373T</emphasis>) is reported for services to a patient who presents with one or more destructive behavior(s).</para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>The service time is based on a single technician's face-to-face time with the patient and not the combined time of multiple technicians.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>The physician/QHP must be on-site and immediately available during the service described by <emphasis role="bold">0373T</emphasis>.</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="italics">Examples</emphasis> ▶ <emphasis role="bold">A 5-year-old child previously showed steady improvements in language and social skills at home as a result of 1:1 intensive applied behavior analysis intervention, but skill development seems to have recently reached a plateau.</emphasis> A QHP modifies the previously used written protocols to incorporate procedures designed to build the child's language and social skills into daily home routines (eg, play, dressing, mealtimes). The QHP demonstrates the procedures to the technician and directs the technician to implement the protocols with the child. The QHP observes and provides feedback as the technician implements the procedures with the child. The technician's face-to-face time with the patient is 45 minutes. Code <emphasis role="bold">97155</emphasis> is reported with 3 units of service.</para>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="italics">Teaching Point:</emphasis> Time spent by the technician and QHP without the patient present is not included in the time of service.</para>
            <para>▶<emphasis role="bold">A 13-year-old teen is reported to beisolated from peers because of poor social skills and odd behavior.</emphasis> The teen attends a group treatment session that focuses on peer social skills. A QHP begins the group session by asking each patient to briefly describe 2 of their recent social encounters with peers, one that went well and one that did not. The information is used to develop a group activity through which each patient can practice the skills they used in the encounters that went well and can problem-solve the interactions that did not go well. The QHP helps each patient identify social cues that were recognized correctly and incorrectly and what they could have done differently. The QHP also provides prompts and feedback individualized to each patient's skills. The QHP ends the session by summarizing the discussion. The total time of the session was 70 minutes, including a 10-minute break (ie, 60 minutes of group session). Code <emphasis role="bold">97158</emphasis> is reported with 4 units of service.</para>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="italics">Teaching Point:</emphasis> Only the QHP's face-to-face time spent providing the service is reported.</para>
            <para>▶<emphasis role="bold">A 16-year-old teen has had 2 surgical procedures to relieve esophageal blockages caused by pica involving repeat ingestion of small metal objects (eg, paper clips, pushpins).</emphasis> The patient's pica behavior has not responded to previous treatment. The QHP supervising the patient's treatment plan has previously developed written protocols for reducing the patient's pica. A technician carefully inspects the room before the session to make sure no potential pica items are accessible to the patient. Two technicians are present, with one guiding the patient through a series of trials in which the patient is presented with a food item and a nonhazardous item that resembles a pica item. The second technician prompts the patient to choose the food item and blocks attempts to choose the pica item. The patient's response to each trial is recorded. The QHP is on-site and available to assist as needed. The total session lasts 40 minutes. Code <emphasis role="bold">0373T</emphasis> is reported with 3 units.</para>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="italics">Teaching Point:</emphasis> Although 2 technicians were present, time is counted only once. The midpoint rule allows reporting a unit of service for the final 10 minutes of service.</para>
         </sect4>
         <sect4 id="ch0015s0004s0001s01s04">
            <title>Family Adaptive Behavior Treatment Guidance (97156–97157)</title>
            <para>Family adaptive behavior treatment guidance (<emphasis role="bold">97156</emphasis>) and multiple-family group adaptive behavior treatment guidance (<emphasis role="bold">97157</emphasis>) are administered by a physician or QHP face-to-face with guardian(s)/caregiver(s) and involve identifying potential treatment targets and training guardian(s)/caregiver(s) to implement treatment protocols designed to address deficient adaptive or maladaptive behaviors.</para>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="bold">#97156</emphasis> Family adaptive behavior treatment guidance, administered by physician or other QHP (with or without the patient present), face-to-face with guardian(s)/caregiver(s), each 15 minutes <emphasis role="bold">#97157</emphasis> Multiple-family group adaptive behavior treatment guidance, administered by physician or other QHP (without the patient present), face-to-face with multiple sets of guardians/caregivers, each 15 minutes</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Family adaptive behavior treatment guidance (<emphasis role="bold">97156</emphasis>) provided to the caregiver(s) of 1 patient may be performed with or without the patient present. Adaptive behavior treatment in which the parent(s) or guardian(s) are present but not part of the therapy would not qualify as family adaptive behavior treatment.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Family adaptive behavior treatment guidance provided to the caregiver(s) of multiple patients (<emphasis role="bold">97157</emphasis>) is performed without the patients present. The group must be no larger than the caregiver(s) of 8 patients. <emphasis role="italics">CPT</emphasis> does not include a code for reporting services to a group of 9 or more patients.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>▶ The parents of a 6-year-old child seek training in procedures for helping the child communicate through picture cards during typical family routines, a skill he previously developed in adaptive behavior treatment therapy sessions with technicians. A physician/QHP trains the parents. The service includes reviewing the written treatment and data collection protocols with the parents, demonstrating how to implement the cards in role-playing and with the child, and having the parents implement the protocols with the child while the provider observes and provides feedback. The time of service is 1 hour.</para>
            <para>Code <emphasis role="bold">97156</emphasis> is reported with 4 units of service.</para>
            <para>▶ The parents of a 3-year-old child who has pervasive hyperactivity and no functional play, social, or communication skills seek training inhow to manage his hyperactive and disruptive behavior and help him develop appropriate play, social, and communication skills. The parents attend a group session (without the patient) led by a physician who asks each set of parents to identify 1 skill to be increased or 1 problem behavior to be decreased in their own child. The physician describes how behavior analytic principles and procedures could be applied to the behavior identified by the parents of the 3-year-old patient. The physician demonstrates a procedure (eg, prompting the child to speak instead of whining when he wants something; not giving him preferred items when he whines). The parents then role-play, implementing that procedure. Other group participants and the physician provide feedback and make constructive suggestions. That process is repeated for skills/behaviors identified by other sets of parents. The group session ends with the physician summarizing the main points, answering questions, and giving each set of parents a homework assignment to practice the skills they worked on during the session. The session lasts 110 minutes. Code <emphasis role="bold">97157</emphasis> is reported with 7 units.</para>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="bold">Teaching Point:</emphasis> The last 5 minutes is not reported because the midpoint of 8 minutes beyond the last full 15-minute period (105 minutes) was not passed.</para>
         </sect4>
      </sect3>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="ch0015s0004s0002">
      <title>Habilitative and Rehabilitative Modifiers (96, 97)</title>
      <para>Adaptive behavior services may be either habilitative or rehabilitative. <emphasis role="italics">Habilitative</emphasis> services help an individual learn skills not yet developed and keep and/or improve those skills. <emphasis role="italics">Rehabilitative</emphasis> services help a patient keep, get back, or improve skills that have been lost or limited because of illness, injury, and/or disability. Because the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act requires that certain health plans provide equal coverage for habilitative and rehabilitative services and count each type of service separately, it may be necessary to indicate that a service is habilitative or rehabilitative. Modifiers <emphasis role="bold">96</emphasis> (habilitative services) and <emphasis role="bold">97</emphasis> (rehabilitative services) are appended to procedure codes to designate the nature of a service. Modifiers <emphasis role="bold">96</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">97</emphasis> may not be adopted for use by all payers or may have limited utility. Verify payer policies for these modifiers when providing habilitative and rehabilitative services.</para>
   </sect2>
   <sect2 id="ch0015s0004s0003">
      <title>Other Nonphysician Qualified Health Care Professional Services</title>
      <sect3 id="ch0015s0004s30009">
         <title/>
         <sect4 id="ch0015s0004s0003s01s01">
            <title>Medical Team Conferences (99366, 99368)</title>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="bold">99366</emphasis> Medical team conference with interdisciplinary team of health care professionals, face-to-face with patient and/or family, 30 minutes or more; participation by nonphysician qualified health care professional <emphasis role="bold">99368</emphasis> Medical team conference with interdisciplinary team of health care professionals, patient and/or family not present, 30 minutes or more; participation by nonphysician qualified health care professional Although included in the E/M section of <emphasis role="italics">CPT</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">99366</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">99368</emphasis> are reported for services by NQHCPs. Physicians and QHPs report team conference participation without the patient or caregiver present with <emphasis role="bold">99367</emphasis>. Refer to Chapter 9 for more information.</para>
            <para>Medical team conference codes are used to report participation by a minimum of 3 health care professionals, including physicians, QHPs, and NQHCPs, of different specialties in conferences to coordinate or manage care and services for established patients with chronic or multiple health conditions (eg, a child with ventilator dependence and developmental delays, seizures, and a gastrostomy tube for nutrition).</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Codes differentiate between face-to-face (<emphasis role="bold">99366</emphasis>) and non–face-to-face (patient and/or family is not present [<emphasis role="bold">99368</emphasis>]) team conference services.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Medicaid and commercial payers may follow these Medicare requirements or have their own specific rules.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>One unit of service is reported for each conference of 30 minutes or more.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Medical team conferences require</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>In-person participation by a minimum of 3 health care professionals (any combination of NQHCPs, physicians, and/or QHPs) from different subspecialties or disciplines (eg, speech pathologists, dietitians, social workers), with or without the patient, family member(s), community agencies, surrogate decision-maker(s) (eg, legal guardian), and/or caregiver(s) as <emphasis role="italics">CPT</emphasis> does not include <emphasis role="bold">99366</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">99368</emphasis> in the codes reportable for telemedicine services</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Verify payer policies for care team conferences. Although payment for <emphasis role="bold">99366</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">99368</emphasis> is bundled into payment for other services in the Medicare Physician Fee Schedule, some benefit plans allow separate payment when an NQHCP participates either in person or virtually.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Active involvement in developing, revising, coordinating, and implementing health care services needed by the patient by each participant</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>That the participant has provided face-to-face evaluation(s) and/or treatment to the patient, separate from any team conference, within the previous 60 days</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Only 1 individual from the same specialty to report <emphasis role="bold">99366–99368</emphasis> for the same encounter</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Medical record documentation that supports the reporting individual's participation, the time spent from the beginning of review of an individual patient until the conclusion of review, and the contributed information and subsequent treatment recommendations</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Medical team conferences may not be reported when ✖ The facility or organization is contractually obligated to provide the service, or the conferences are informal meetings or simple conversations between physicians and NQHCPs (eg, therapists).</para>
            <para>✖ Less than 30 minutes of conference time is spent in a team conference.</para>
            <para>▶ A care team meets to discuss the care plans for a 4-year-old child with history of congenital heart disease, cerebrovascular injury with residual paraplegia, and developmental delays. As the child nears entry to kindergarten, the pediatrician has requested input to the child's individualized education program and ongoing health care plan from all health care professionals. The pediatrician, cardiologist, physiatrist, occupational and physical therapists, speech pathologist, home care coordinator, and social worker attend the conference to discuss the child's current medical status, prognosis for the short and long term, and necessary accommodations for her education. The conference lasts 60 minutes. The patient and family are not present for the conference.</para>
            <para>Nonphysician qualified health care professionals report participation using <emphasis role="bold">99368</emphasis> when the patient or caregivers are not present. Assign appropriate <emphasis role="italics">ICD-10-CM</emphasis> codes for the specified developmental delays (codes in categories <emphasis role="bold">F80–F88</emphasis>) and other health concerns addressed.</para>
         </sect4>
      </sect3>
   </sect2>
</sect1>