<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="ch0007s0003">
   <sect1info>
      <risinfo>
         <risprev>sect1.9781610028370.ch0007s0002</risprev>
         <riscurrent>sect1.9781610028370.ch0007s0003</riscurrent>
         <risnext>sect1.9781610028370.ch0007s0004</risnext>
         <booktitle>Coding for Pediatrics 2026</booktitle>
         <isbn>9781610028370</isbn>
         <chapternumber>7</chapternumber>
         <chapterid>ch0007</chapterid>
         <chaptertitle>5. Preventing Fraud and Abuse: Compliance, Audits, and Paybacks</chaptertitle>
         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <personname>
                  <firstname>Linda D.</firstname>
                  <surname>Parsi</surname>
               </personname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <publisher>
            <publishername>American Academy of Pediatrics</publishername>
         </publisher>
         <pubdate>2025</pubdate>
      </risinfo>
      <primaryauthor>
         <personname>
            <firstname>Linda D.</firstname>
            <surname>Parsi</surname>
         </personname>
      </primaryauthor>
   </sect1info>
   <title>Compliance Programs</title>
   <para>Does your practice have a fraud and abuse prevention compliance program? For many years, compliance programs for small practices were voluntary. They are now required. Section 6401(a) of the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act requires physicians and other providers and suppliers who enroll in Medicare, Medicaid, or the Children's Health Insurance Program (CHIP) to establish a compliance program with certain "core elements." This applies even for small practices, but the compliance program can be designed to meet the needs and capabilities of the practice.</para>
   <para>A compliance program establishes strategies to prevent, detect, and resolve conduct that does not conform to</para>
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>Federal and state law</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Federal, state, and private payer health care program requirements</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>The practice's own ethical and business policies</para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>Pediatric practices benefit from compliance programs in many ways. A compliance program should support</para>
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Billing and coding accuracy and avoidance of missed opportunities to appropriately collect earned revenue</emphasis>
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Improved documentation that may prevent malpractice</emphasis>
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">A practice's defense against insurance company takebacks</emphasis>
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Billing and coding patterns that eliminate the practice as a target of fraud investigation</emphasis>
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Staff training, including sending a clear message to all staff that compliance with practice policies and procedures is required</emphasis>
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Guidance of any staff who may be unsure of compliance risks related to a situation (eg, responding to a patient's request to alter codes on a medical claim)</emphasis>
         </para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>Practices with written compliance programs report better control over internal procedures, improved medical record documentation, and streamlined practice operations.</para>
   <sect2 id="ch0007s0003s20001">
      <title/>
      <sect3 id="ch0007s0003s30003">
         <title/>
         <sect4 id="ch0007s0003s0001s01s01">
            <title>The 7 Elements of the HHS OIG Compliance Program</title>
            <para>The 7 core elements described in the HHS OIG guidance for compliance programs for small physician practices published in 2023 are</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Implement written compliance and practice standards.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Designate a compliance officer, contact, or team.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Conduct appropriate training and education.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Conduct internal monitoring and auditing.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Respond appropriately to detected offenses and develop corrective action.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Develop open lines of communication.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Enforce disciplinary standards through well-publicized guidelines.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>It is also useful to consult the <emphasis role="italics">United States Sentencing Commission Guidelines Manual</emphasis> (www.ussc.gov/guidelines), which makes it clear that an organization under investigation may be given more sympathetic treatment if a good compliance program is in place. Compliance programs not only help prevent fraudulent or erroneous claims but also show that the physician practice is making a good faith effort to submit claims appropriately. However, that would require the program to be integrated into the daily operations of the practice; it cannot be a set of policies and procedures merely kept in a binder or on a computer unrelated to actual business operations.</para>
            <para>Here are some reasons cited by the <emphasis role="italics">United States Sentencing Commission Guidelines Manual</emphasis> to implement an effective compliance program.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>It may save the practice money if it prevents costly civil suits and criminal investigations.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>It sends anunambiguous message to employees that fraud and abuse will not betolerated.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>It decreases the risk of employees suing the practice under the False Claims Act because employees will have an internal communication system for reporting questionable activities and resolving problems.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>It helps if an investigation occurs. Investigators may be more inclined to resolve the problem as a civil rather than a criminal matter, or it may lead to an administrative resolution rather than a formal false claim action.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>It may help reduce the range used for imposing fines under federal sentencing guidelines.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>It may influence an HHS OIG decision on whether to exclude a provider from participation in federal health care programs.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>It frequently results in improved medical record documentation.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>It improves coding accuracy, reduces denials, and makes claims and payment processes more effective.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>It educates physicians and employees on their responsibilities for preventing, detecting, and reporting physician fraud and abuse.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>It should meet governmental requirements for practices to have a formal compliance plan.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect4>
      </sect3>
   </sect2>
</sect1>