<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="ch0016s0002">
   <sect1info>
      <risinfo>
         <risprev>sect1.9781610028370.</risprev>
         <riscurrent>sect1.9781610028370.ch0016s0002</riscurrent>
         <risnext>sect1.9781610028370.ch0016s0003</risnext>
         <booktitle>Coding for Pediatrics 2026</booktitle>
         <isbn>9781610028370</isbn>
         <chapternumber>16</chapternumber>
         <chapterid>ch0016</chapterid>
         <chaptertitle>13. Surgery, Infusion, and Sedation in the Outpatient Setting</chaptertitle>
         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <personname>
                  <firstname>Linda D.</firstname>
                  <surname>Parsi</surname>
               </personname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <publisher>
            <publishername>American Academy of Pediatrics</publishername>
         </publisher>
         <pubdate>2025</pubdate>
      </risinfo>
      <primaryauthor>
         <personname>
            <firstname>Linda D.</firstname>
            <surname>Parsi</surname>
         </personname>
      </primaryauthor>
   </sect1info>
   <title>Surgery, Infusion, and Sedation in the Outpatient Setting</title>
   <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">
        Chapter 13
      </emphasis>
   </para>
   <para>indicates a new code; ▲, revised; #, re-sequenced; ✚, add-on; ✱, audiovisual technology; and ♦, synchronous interactive audio.</para>
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>Components included in the surgical package for services assigned a global period</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Separately reportable medication and supply codes</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Evaluation and management (E/M) services provided in conjunction with procedures</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Reporting reduced or terminated services</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Discussion of codes for some commonly performed procedural services</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Reporting contraceptive services (ie, injection, insertion, or implant)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Selecting appropriate initial and subsequent codes for hydration and infusion services</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Reporting moderate sedation by the same or different physician performing the procedure for which sedation is required</para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <sect2 id="ch0016s0002s0001">
      <title>Procedural Services in the Office or Other Outpatient Setting</title>
      <para>This chapter reviews coding for procedural services including minor surgical procedures, fracture care, and injections and infusions.</para>
      <para>The commonly used Medicare global periods and total non-facility relative value units (RVUs) are provided for reference for many procedures discussed in this chapter. The RVUs included are from the 2025 Medicare Physician Fee Schedule (MPFS) and are not geographically adjusted (2026 RVUs were unavailable at the time of this publication). Individual payers may not use Medicare global periods and/or current-year Medicare RVUs. Check contract terms and payer policies for payer-specific information.</para>
   </sect2>
</sect1>