<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="ch0006s0004">
   <sect1info>
      <risinfo>
         <risprev>sect1.9781610028370.ch0006s0003</risprev>
         <riscurrent>sect1.9781610028370.ch0006s0004</riscurrent>
         <risnext>sect1.9781610028370.ch0006s0005</risnext>
         <booktitle>Coding for Pediatrics 2026</booktitle>
         <isbn>9781610028370</isbn>
         <chapternumber>6</chapternumber>
         <chapterid>ch0006</chapterid>
         <chaptertitle>4. The Business of Medicine: Working With Current and Emerging Payment Systems</chaptertitle>
         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <personname>
                  <firstname>Linda D.</firstname>
                  <surname>Parsi</surname>
               </personname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <publisher>
            <publishername>American Academy of Pediatrics</publishername>
         </publisher>
         <pubdate>2025</pubdate>
      </risinfo>
      <primaryauthor>
         <personname>
            <firstname>Linda D.</firstname>
            <surname>Parsi</surname>
         </personname>
      </primaryauthor>
   </sect1info>
   <title>CHAPTER 4. THE BUSINESS OF MEDICINE: WORKING WITH CURRENT AND EMERGING PAYMENT SYSTEMS</title>
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>Benchmarks are often like the National Committee for Quality Assurance Healthcare Effectiveness Data and Information Set (HEDIS) quality metrics (some common metrics for pediatrics include rates of immunizations; rates of patient adherence to Early and Periodic Screening, Diagnostic, and Treatment visits; and rates of appropriate prescription of asthma medications). These metrics should be relevant to pediatrics. Other potential pediatric-specific measures include the 2026 Core Set of Children's Health Care Quality Measures for Medicaid and CHIP (www.medicaid.gov/medicaid/quality-of-care/downloads/2026-child-core-set.pdf).</para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>When entering into pay-for-performance agreements, a practice may request use of the same standardized measure set across all payers to simplify performance tracking.</para>
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>Benchmarks based on transparent rubrics allow providers to track their performance against the benchmark on an ongoing basis. In contrast, if benchmarks are based on comparison with peers, providers might not know whether they meet the metrics until the end of the reporting period.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Payers should provide information on how benchmarks are defined and measured. Practices should also ensure that benchmarks come from pediatric peers with similar patients to avoid comparison with practices that treat only patients whose conditions are less medically and/or socially complex. When benchmarks are not limited to pediatric peers, they should include adjustments to consider the lower expense to payers for pediatric-specific care.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Practices should also provide quarterly data on provider performance against benchmarks. This way, providers are aware of their performance standing and have an opportunity to improve throughout the measurement incentive year.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Providers should berewarded for achieving incremental improvements and maintaining high levels of quality once achieved.</para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>When considering whether to participate inone of these alternative payment models, practices need to determine expected costs and utilization and assess whether they can deliver services under the projected budget. Using CPT codes and their RVUs will aid in this assessment. Projections can be made from RVUs of the services currently provided and projected to be provided with consideration of changes such as decreased number or complexity of patient visits resulting from better-coordinated care. With these types of data, the practice can assess the effect of new payment methodologies on its bottom line.</para>
   <sect2 id="ch0006s0004s20001">
      <title/>
      <sect3 id="ch0006s0004s30002">
         <title/>
         <sect4 id="ch0006s0004s0001s01s01">
            <title>Important Considerations Regarding Payer Ratings in Value-Based Care Models</title>
            <para>In value-based payment programs, payers may publish ratings and cost-of-care comparisons of practices within a community to guide a family's selection of a practice or physician. In addition, some payers prefer to drive patients to high-value practices or have tiered co-payments based on individual physician or practice performance. Families interpret ratings to reflect a lower quality of care rather than a lower cost of care.</para>
            <para>When discussing publication of practice ratings and/or cost comparisons with payers, practices should be aware of whether immunizations and preventive care are counted in the total cost of care. Otherwise, they may find that if they improve well-child visit and immunization rates, the costs of those services are counted against the practice in total cost-of-care calculations.</para>
            <para>In some parts of the country, practices can earn additional incentives if the total cost of care for patients compares favorably with that of geographically and specialty matched peers. In addition, some payers incentivize around "care efficiency measures" (eg, avoidance of antibiotic treatment for acute bronchitis/bronchiolitis: ages 3 months to 17 years). Both of these are often risk adjusted according to claims data about the overall patient population of the practice. Payers should define measures (eg, what constitutes anavoidable emergency department [ED] visit) and data that can be used to improve performance. As with other quality or cost measures, these measures should be relevant to pediatrics.</para>
         </sect4>
         <sect4 id="ch0006s0004s0001s01s02">
            <title>Participating in Alternative Payment Models</title>
            <para>Value-based payment models are already in place for pediatrics in some geographic areas and may soon be adopted in others. Whether your practice provides primary or specialty care, there are steps you should take to prepare for success. When payment is based on the costs of care and patient experience, practices must take responsibility for keeping costs low and keeping quality of care and patient experience high. Steps that practices may take include</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Learning more about value-based payment options</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Generating and using reports of your costs, quality measurement, and other data</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Learning who your active patients are and staying up to date through routine data analysis</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Increasing access to care beyond traditional office-based care (eg, telemedicine, care management services, remote patient monitoring).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Seeking to remove inefficiencies by reviewing routine tasks and patient flow. Provide staff with incentives and an expectation to create consistency and efficiency.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>When considering an alternative payment model contract, seeking expert consultation to help identify and, as necessary, negotiate points of concern within the contract.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Learning about the communities of your patients (ie, school and community resources, school schedules, average income and education of caregivers, urgent and emergency care utilization patterns) and using that information in providing care.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Considering options for adding nonphysician health care professionals to your practice, such as care coordinators, patient educators, and emotional/behavioral health specialists. (These clinicians may also add separately reportable services under FFS contracts.)</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Steps that may increase successful participation in value-based payment include</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Setting shared goals and shared priorities with the payer</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <itemizedlist>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>Evaluate your progress against goals and renegotiate targets each year with the payer. Targets might need to be adjusted depending on past achievements and future opportunities.</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Being aware of and collaborating with other health care providers who care for patients attributed to the practice</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <itemizedlist>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>Recognize that every provider within and outside your practice must contribute to not only reducing the cost of care but improving the quality of care to reduce the practice's risk under new payment models.</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <itemizedlist>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>Collaborate with other health care professionals to ensure that patients receive evidence-based and cost-effective care, including consideration of formulary and total cost of coordinated care.</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Remember that care received in the ED and urgent care clinics and from subspecialists or NQHCPs (eg, physical therapists) is included in the cost of care attributed to your cost to care for your patients.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Optimizing data systems</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Embedding clinical guidelines into care delivery through protocols and reminders — Configuring and using your electronic health record (EHR) and other automated systems to promote efficiency (eg, display generic drugs first when a brand name is entered)</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Other considerations for pediatricians include</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Recognizing that, depending on how the payment model is set up, managing a healthy population of patients may not result insignificant cost savings.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Having the ability to access and monitor patient population and performance metric data, which is important for successful participation innew payment methodologies. Physicians must be aware of not only the patients they are seeing but also those who are not receiving preventive and/or follow-up care.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Making a plan with staff to perform post-payment follow-upand address inconsistencies between your records and the payer's record of services to ensure you are credited appropriately for services provided.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>For physicians, understanding the links between new payment methodologies and data collection to support quality metrics (eg, failure to report codes for screening services performed may result in negative performance measurement and lost opportunity for enhanced payment).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Remembering that in states where the Children's Health Insurance Program (CHIP) operates independent of a Medicaid program, children covered by CHIP may or may not be included innew payment methodologies and/or performance measurement.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect4>
         <sect4 id="ch0006s0004s0001s01s03">
            <title>Organizational Support for Entering Value-Based Payment Contracts</title>
            <para>Demonstrating that a practice provides care at a lower cost and higher value can significantly burden small practices. Entering into a contract to participate in a network or an organization with other physician practices, and sometimes hospitals or health care systems, can offer support on multiple levels. Through these contractual relationships, physicians may achieve objectives such as improved capitation rates, entrance into other risk-sharing contracts, and increased ability to demonstrate quality and cost reductions. There are multiple types of contractual entities that can influence success in value-based payment arrangements.</para>
         </sect4>
         <sect4 id="ch0006s0004s0001s01s04">
            <title>Identify the Practice's Payer Mix</title>
            <para>Current and accurate information on payer mix and potential value/loss to the practice is essential in making participation decisions.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Know how many patients you have in each plan and what percentage of your total patients that represents. In addition, know what percentage of RVUs each payer pays for your most frequently used codes and how these percentages compare with each other in terms of payment.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect4>
      </sect3>
   </sect2>
</sect1>