<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="ch0029s0007">
   <sect1info>
      <risinfo>
         <risprev>sect1.9781610028370.ch0029s0006</risprev>
         <riscurrent>sect1.9781610028370.ch0029s0007</riscurrent>
         <risnext>sect1.9781610028370.ch0029s0008</risnext>
         <booktitle>Coding for Pediatrics 2026</booktitle>
         <isbn>9781610028370</isbn>
         <chapternumber>29</chapternumber>
         <chapterid>ch0029</chapterid>
         <chaptertitle>Appendix II. Test Your Knowledge! Answer Key</chaptertitle>
         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <personname>
                  <firstname>Linda D.</firstname>
                  <surname>Parsi</surname>
               </personname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <publisher>
            <publishername>American Academy of Pediatrics</publishername>
         </publisher>
         <pubdate>2025</pubdate>
      </risinfo>
      <primaryauthor>
         <personname>
            <firstname>Linda D.</firstname>
            <surname>Parsi</surname>
         </personname>
      </primaryauthor>
   </sect1info>
   <title>
      Chapter 10
    </title>
   <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">1. b.</emphasis>
      <emphasis role="italics">Nonphysician qualified health care professional</emphasis> is used to describe professionals (eg, licensed clinical psychologists and licensed clinical social workers) who may provide and independently report non-E/M services as allowed by state regulations and payer policy.</para>
   <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">2. d.</emphasis> Psychiatric collaborative care management (<emphasis role="bold">99492–99494</emphasis>) represents services provided by a team that includes 3 distinct roles: a treating physician or QHP, BHCM, and psychiatric consultant.</para>
   <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">3. c.</emphasis> Report testing evaluation services according to the face-to-face time with the patient and the time spent integrating and interpreting data. A minimum of 31 minutes must be provided to report a 1-hour unit of service. Time spent by technicians (eg, in test administration and scoring) is not included.</para>
   <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">4. b.</emphasis> Health and behavior assessment and intervention procedures (<emphasis role="bold">96156, 96158, 96159,</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">96164–96171</emphasis>) are provided by NQHCPs who cannot report E/M services but can independently provide and report assessment and intervention procedures. Physicians and QHPs who can provide and report E/M services do not report these codes.</para>
   <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">5. d.</emphasis> Although family members may act as informants during individual psychotherapy, psychotherapy using family psychotherapy techniques is reported with <emphasis role="bold">90846</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">90847</emphasis> depending on whether the patient is present for the service. When multiple families participate in family psychotherapy at the same session, <emphasis role="bold">90849</emphasis> is reported once for each family.</para>
</sect1>