<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="ch0012s0002">
   <sect1info>
      <risinfo>
         <risprev>sect1.9781610028370.</risprev>
         <riscurrent>sect1.9781610028370.ch0012s0002</riscurrent>
         <risnext>sect1.9781610028370.ch0012s0003</risnext>
         <booktitle>Coding for Pediatrics 2026</booktitle>
         <isbn>9781610028370</isbn>
         <chapternumber>12</chapternumber>
         <chapterid>ch0012</chapterid>
         <chaptertitle>9. Indirect Management of Chronic and Complex Conditions</chaptertitle>
         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <personname>
                  <firstname>Linda D.</firstname>
                  <surname>Parsi</surname>
               </personname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <publisher>
            <publishername>American Academy of Pediatrics</publishername>
         </publisher>
         <pubdate>2025</pubdate>
      </risinfo>
      <primaryauthor>
         <personname>
            <firstname>Linda D.</firstname>
            <surname>Parsi</surname>
         </personname>
      </primaryauthor>
   </sect1info>
   <title>Indirect Management of Chronic and Complex Conditions</title>
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>Options for reporting evaluation and management (E/M) services provided without direct patient contact</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Tracking time of services provided within a 30-day or calendar-month period</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Differentiating types of care management services provided to improve care for chronic conditions</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Providing and reporting care management services during a patient's transition from a facility stay to the community setting</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>Related but separately reported indirect management services</para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>In addition to codes for services provided on a single date of service, <emphasis role="italics">Current Procedural Terminology (CPT®)</emphasis> includes categories of codes created to recognize episodes of care for complex health care needs that go beyond the work included in preservice, intraservice, and postservice values of the traditional E/M service provided directly (in person or by telecommunications technology) by a physician or other qualified health care professional (QHP) whose scope of practice includes E/M services (eg, nurse practitioner, physician associate). Several code categories include codes for reporting care management services performed by clinical staff under the supervision of a physician or QHP and for reporting a combination of physician or QHP and clinical staff services.</para>
   <para>The American Academy of Pediatrics (AAP) <emphasis role="italics">Pediatric Care Management: Coding Quick Reference Card 2026</emphasis> outlines these codes and includes decision trees to help guide users to the correct codes (www.aap.org/Pediatric-Care-Management-Coding-Quick-Reference-Card-2026).</para>
</sect1>